Guide to the Luther Evans Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Luther Evans Papers,
1952-1970
Evans, Luther Harris, 1902-1981.
23 linear ft (ca.27,000 items in 54 boxes).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4079697
Biographical Note
Educator & librarian. He was Director of the Historical Records Survey, Director of the Legislative Reference Service at the Library of Congress, Librarian of Congress from 1945 to 1953, Director General of UNESCO, and Director of the international and legal collections at the Columbia University Libraries, 1962-1971.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, reports, and printed materials. The papers, which consist to a large extent of mimeographed and printed reports of various organizations with which Evans was affiliated, chronicle a wide range of his activities in the fields of law, international relations, and library service. Among the cataloged correspondents are: Dorothy Canfield Fisher, Norman Cousins, S. Radhakrishnan, and Paul H. Douglas.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 11 series:
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Federal Library Survey Project
Series III: U.N. International Cooperation Year
Series IV: UNESCO
Series V: Copyright
Series VI: Universities and The Quest For Peace
Series VII: Commission To Study The Organization Of Peace
Series VIII: American Civil Libertties Union
Series IX: Miscellaneous Subjects
Series X: United States Committee For Refugees
Series XI: Printed Material
Subjects
Library of Congress.; Unesco.; American Civil Liberties Union.; Cousins, Norman.; Douglas, Paul H. (Paul Howard), 1892-1976.; Fisher, Dorothy Canfield, 1879-1958.; Radhakrishnan, S. (Sarvepalli), 1888-1975.; United States--Foreign relations--1945-1989.; Government libraries.; International agencies.; International relations.; Law.; Library science--Societies, etc.; Library science.; Political refugees.; Agenda.; Memoranda.; Minutes.; Reports.; Educators.; Librarians.; Government executives--United States.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 2-55. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
M-1975 Evans, Luther Gift
Gift of Luther Evans, 1975 & 1976.
Transfer from Lehman Library, 1986.
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Cataloged letters (Box 1)
  - UNESCO Correspondence, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, miscellaneous, 1960s (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Series II: Federal Library Survey Project
  - 1954-1962 (Box 3)
  - 1954-1962 - loose (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and drafts (Box 5)
  - Manuscripts (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous reports, (5 boxes) (Box 7-11)
  - Miscellaneous material, (2 boxes) (Box 12 & 13)
- Series III: U.N. International Cooperation Year
  - Memoranda, reports and printed material, 1965 (Box 14)
- Series IV: UNESCO
  - Clippings and releases, 1953-1955, (3 boxes) (Box 15-17)
  - Reprints and memoranda, 1962-1965, (4 boxes) (Box 18-21)
  - Memoranda and reports, ca. 1955-1970, (2 boxes) (Box 22 & 23)
  - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO Memoranda and reports, ca. 1955-1970, (2 boxes) (Box 24-26)
- Series V: Copyright
  - Correspondence and reprints, 1964-1967, (2 boxes) (Box 27 & 28)
- Series VI: Universities and The Quest For Peace
  - Correspondence and related material, 1962-1969, (3 boxes) (Box 29-31)
- Series VII: Commission To Study The Organization Of Peace
  - Memoranda, reports and some correspondence, (4 boxes) (Box 32-35)
  - Printed materials (Box 36)
- Series VIII: American Civil Libertties Union
  - 1964-1966 (Box 37)
  - Adgendas, memoranda, minutes, etc., 1962-1964 (Box 38)
  - Adgendas, memoranda, minutes, etc., 1964-1969 (Box 39)
  - Adgendas, memoranda, minutes, etc., 1963-1969 (Box 40 & 41)
  - Committees (Box 42 & 43)
  - Undated (Box 44)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 45 & 46)
  - Printed and mimeograph material (Box 47 & 48)
  - Printed material (Box 49 & 50)
- Series IX: Miscellaneous Subjects
  - Columbia University (Box 51)
  - George Washington (Box 51)
  - Luis Alberto Sanchez (Box 51)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 51)
- Series X: United States Committee For Refugees
  - Memoranda, minutes and printed material (Box 52-54)
- Series XI: Printed Material
  - Miscellaneous printed items (Box 55)